<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="atom.xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://stomastrap.com/blog</id>
    <title>StomaStrap Blog</title>
    <updated>2025-08-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://stomastrap.com/blog"/>
    <subtitle>StomaStrap Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://stomastrap.com/img/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Store Closed]]></title>
        <id>https://stomastrap.com/blog/storeclosed</id>
        <link href="https://stomastrap.com/blog/storeclosed"/>
        <updated>2025-08-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[I stopped paying Shopify after the 3 month trial ran out. The only StomaStrap I sold was to myself (to make sure the shipping labels and payment would work).]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I stopped paying Shopify after the 3 month trial ran out. The only StomaStrap I sold was to myself (to make sure the shipping labels and payment would work).</p>
<p>Still wear my StomaStrap every day, still getting 1 week wear time most weeks. But I've got clients I need to do engineering work for, and this side project
hasn't bourne much fruit.</p>
<p>Still, it's something. Doing something is better than nothing. So there's that.</p>
<p>Feel free to ping me if you think a StomaStrap would work for you. I can send you the files to have some nice kid at the library print them out from their
3D printers. Or maybe I'll be your new friend and do that for you.</p>
<p>~Ed</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ed Hubbell</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/edhubbell</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Price Cuts]]></title>
        <id>https://stomastrap.com/blog/pricecuts</id>
        <link href="https://stomastrap.com/blog/pricecuts"/>
        <updated>2025-04-24T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We're cutting our prices. I could say that we've received feedback that our]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're cutting our prices. I could say that we've received feedback that our
pricing is too high. This feedback has come in the form of only one sale of a StomaStrap system.</p>
<p>I do know that the customer for that first system is quite satisfied.</p>
<p>As you've probably already guessed, that first customer is me. I had to order a system just to make sure that the Shopify store even works. Plus I needed to make sure I can actually print a shipping label, etc. All those details are now squared away.</p>
<p>So as of 4/24/25, you can still be customer #1. It'll just be order #2. And full systems are now $40, down from $70.</p>
<p>Next steps are to work on some marketing. Maybe a video of my youngest throwing a soccer ball right at my StomaStrap. Plus maybe some product improvements.</p>
<p>~Ed</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ed Hubbell</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/edhubbell</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Soft Opening]]></title>
        <id>https://stomastrap.com/blog/softopening</id>
        <link href="https://stomastrap.com/blog/softopening"/>
        <updated>2025-04-20T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Today is the first day I talked about StomaStrap in a public forum (in a Reddit thread on /r/ostomy). So someone might actually see this site. What's the plan from here?]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today is the first day I talked about StomaStrap in a public forum (in a Reddit thread on <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ostomy/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">/r/ostomy</a>). So someone might actually see this site. What's the plan from here?</p>
<p>I honestly don't know if the solution I use every day will work for other people. I think it will, but starting StomaStrap.com seems to be the only
way to find out.</p>
<p>Guess this means that the store is open. Email me at <a href="mailto:sales@stomastrap.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sales@stomastrap.com</a> if you have questions. Or call me.</p>
<p>If we can sell systems 2 a month, that's enough to pay for the Shopify website. Barely.</p>
<p>If we can sell 5 and find a couple of enthused users, maybe we buy a cheapo Google-Ad to see if that moves any product.</p>
<p>If we sell, say, 10 systems in a month AND we get some good feedback from users, then we pack up our
3D printer and drive down to the <a href="https://www.wocnext.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Wound and Ostomy care conference in Orlando</a>.
It would be fun to talk to WOC nurses while the printer jams out new support systems. Plus the chance to
talk to people about the possibilities of custom designed ostomy solutions.</p>
<p>If we sell like 20 a month, I'm going to have to get my kids working on filling orders and printing product (I have a day job doing regular engineering type things). Plus maybe some more color options.</p>
<p>What if we sell more? Well, then we'll just need to listen to our customers. I've been wearing a version with the same dimensions
for about a year. It took a while to get the design down. What if someone needs supports that are 2mm higher? A fatter ring? Can we
offer customizable product via a web interface? Absolutely, if there's demand for it.</p>
<p>Support for some wafer or bag that I've never seen? That's motivating. Got a wafer that we don't support, but looks like it'd work? Contact me and we'll see what we can do.</p>
<p>Want to see where I'm coming from? You can click to view you're not squeamish.</p>
<div><div aria-live="polite"><img style="filter:blur(2.5rem)" src="https://stomastrap.com/img/spoiler/220902/SentMeHomeLikeThis.jpg" alt=""></div></div>
<p>This was me in Sept 2022. Just back from a 40 day hospital stay after complications from rectal cancer surgery. That I'm home and able to get some sleep must be why I'm smiling, because that is a hell of a wound to put a bag on.</p>
<p>That open abdomen contained multiple fistulae. It was like the worst ileostomy ever. Cold drinks came out cold. Here's what it took to bag it.</p>
<div><div aria-live="polite"><img style="filter:blur(2.5rem)" src="https://stomastrap.com/img/spoiler/220902/WoundBag.jpg" alt=""></div></div>
<p>Google photos shows we did about six months of this, with leaks almost weekly, and a dedicated WOC nurse at my house 2x a week. Finally came up with this brace:</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="BagBrace" src="https://stomastrap.com/assets/images/BagBrace-91cafa5c251f3bd92cccad53a6713387.jpg" width="3072" height="4080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>If you want to see what it looked like on:</p>
<div><div aria-live="polite"><img style="filter:blur(2.5rem)" src="https://stomastrap.com/img/spoiler/220902/EdInBagBrace.jpg" alt=""></div></div>
<p>From that time on, I was able to go places without fear of leakage. Trips to the grocery (even though I couldn't eat). Back to working on-site more often.</p>
<p>Lots of medical professionals said 'you should make those - people with fistulas would love that'. So I said 'Great! Give me a call, I'd be happy to make one for someone else.' No one called.</p>
<p>So, there's some backstory. What I'm motivated by is getting solutions out to people that have lost hope. I have been hopeless, depressed, sick, avoided, and slimy with output. Woken up to soaked bedsheets and a ruined mattress pad. Told that the spots on my CT were suspicious for metastatic disease.</p>
<p>So compared to that, possibly failing at an internet 3D-printed medical device venture run out of my basement seems like pretty small potatoes.</p>
<p>And yes, 'soft opening' is a wildly inappropriate pun. That's par for this course.</p>
<p>~Ed</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ed Hubbell</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/edhubbell</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title>
        <id>https://stomastrap.com/blog/welcome</id>
        <link href="https://stomastrap.com/blog/welcome"/>
        <updated>2025-04-09T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We're going to try and get some StomaStrap devices out to ostomates. It's going to take some effort.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We're going to try and get some StomaStrap devices out to ostomates. It's going to take some effort.</p>
<p>I developed the StomaStrap to suit my needs.</p>
<p>And honestly, if no one else needs to use one, that's great. I've got other things to spend my time on.</p>
<p>Here's me in a shirt, wearing a StomaStrap. You can see it, but barely.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="EdInMirror" src="https://stomastrap.com/assets/images/EdInMirror-a02611e658d69f00e5a63a5efca35515.jpg" width="3072" height="4080" class="img_ev3q"></p>
<p>And here it is on. Probably need a better photo than that, but this is a start.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" alt="EdInMirror" src="https://stomastrap.com/assets/images/EdWearingStomaStrap-f510890423cd0a7bcf988628a8418f7f.jpg" width="2736" height="3648" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Ed Hubbell</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/edhubbell</uri>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>